Guide to the David G. and Karen D. Chapman Collection of Photographs of "Famous People of the Old West" circa 1872-1910 PR 375
New-York Historical Society
David G. and Karen D. Chapman collection of photographs of "Famous People of the Old West"
circa 1872-1910
New-York Historical Society
Chapman, David G.
PR 375
1.25 Linear feet (66 tintypes, 4 cartes-de-visite, and 3 cabinet photographs in a three-ring binder and a foamcore enclosure, housed in one flat box).
A collection of 73 photographs purportedly depicting notorious gunfighters, famous lawmen, and other notable figures of the American Old West of the late 19th and early 20th centuries, such as Jesse James, "Doc" Holliday, Wyatt Earp, "Wild Bill" Hickok, and "Buffalo Bill" Cody. The collection was assembled and identified by the late David G. Chapman, an artist, photographer, and reenactor of lawman Bat Masterson. Includes an inventory with image dimensions and a report of compiled biographies of the subjects, and an unrelated, Victorian-era lace paper Valentine's Day card.
Arrangement
The collection is housed in a single, flat box. Images 1 through 70, and 72–73 (called "items" in the container list, below) are stored in protective sheets in a three-ring binder. These images are affixed to their respective pages and may not be removed from the binder. Image 71, which is oversize, is protected by a foamcore enclosure and laid at the bottom of the box. Titles in the container list are copied from those given by the donors' inventory in Folder 1; in some cases these vary slightly from the identification stickers on the image sleeves, which occasionally expand a subject's name or supply fuller details. When available, the archivist has provided the accepted versions of each subject's name, plus his or her life dates, in a note following each item in the container list.
Biographical / Historical
The assembler of the present collection, David G. Chapman (deceased) was born in New York City, where he attended the High School of Art and Design (1960–1964) and the School of Visual Arts (1964–1968). As an artist he specialized in illustrating the human anatomy. As a collector of historic photographs he focused on notable figures from the American Old West. Chapman was also a costumed reenactor of lawman Bartholemew William Barclay "Bat" Masterson (1853–1921), basing his interpretation on the writings of Masterson scholar Robert K. DeArment. [For more on Chapman and his qualifications, see the curriculum vitae and letter at the front of the three-ring binder housing the present collection of photographs.]
Conditions Governing Access
Open to qualified researchers.
Photocopying undertaken by staff only. Limited to twenty exposures of stable, unbound material per day. (Researchers may not accrue unused copy amounts from previous days.)
Immediate Source of Acquisition: Tintypes and supporting documentation
Gift of Karen D. Chapman, Thomas A. Chapman, and Heidi D. Bravo, September 2018 (accession no. PPAC-2018-051).
Credit line for exhibitions: "Gift of David G. and Karen D. Chapman."
Immediate Source of Acquisition: Valentine's Day card
Gift of Karen D. Chapman, 2019 (accession no. PPAC-2019-010).
Credit line for exhibitions: "Gift of Karen D. Chapman and family in memory of the Lane, Driscoll, and Chapman families of Beverly, Massachusetts."
Scope and Contents
The David G. and Karen D. Chapman Collection of Photographs of "Famous People of the Old West" contains 66 tintypes, 4 cartes-de-visite, and 3 cabinet photographs, none of which bear markings or notations to reveal their subjects, but which the donors have identified as the following historical lawmen, outlaws, notable figures, and women who took part in the often violent settlement of the American Old West during the late 19th and early 20th centuries. These identifications have not been confirmed.
Lawmen
• Charlie Bassett
• William Milton "Billy" Breakenridge (1846–1931)
• Timothy Isaiah Courtright, a.k.a. "Jim Courtright," "Longhair Jim," "Big Jim Courtright" (1848–1887)
• Lawrence Edward Deger (1845–1924)
• Virgil Walter Earp (1843–1905)
• Wyatt Berry Stapp Earp (1848–1929)
• "Turkey Creek" Jack Johnson [John Blunt?] (1852–1887)
• Chris Madsen [Christen Madsen Rørmose] (1851–1944)
• Bartholemew William Barclay "Bat" Masterson (1853–1921)
• Edward John "Ed" Masterson (1852–1878)
• Michael Francis "Frank" McClain (1854–1902)
• Mike Meagher (1843–1881)
• Robert H. "Bob" Paul (1831–1901)
• Allan Pinkerton (1819–1884)
• John Henry Selman (1839–1896)
• Thomas James "Bear River" Smith (1830–1870)
• Dallas Stoudenmire (1845–1882)
• Henry Andrew "Heck" Thomas (1850–1912)
• Ben Thompson (1843–1884)
• William Matthew "Bill" Tilghman Jr. (1854–1924)
Outlaws
• William "Curly Bill" Brocius (1845–1882)
• Abraham G. Graham, a.k.a. "Shotgun John Collins" (1851–1922)
• Robert Newton Ford (1862–1892)
• John Wesley Hardin (1853–1895)
• Alexander Franklin "Frank" James (1843–1915)
• Jesse Woodson James (1847–1882)
• William Preston "Wild Bill" Longley (1851–1878)
• Luke L. Short (1854–1893)
• Frank C. Stilwell (1856–1882)
• John Wilson "Texas Jack" or "Shoot-Your-Eye-Out" Vermillion (1842–1911)
Notable figures
• Chalkley Beeson (1855–1912)
• William Frederick "Buffalo Bill" Cody (1846–1917)
• James Cooksey Earp (1841–1926)
• Morgan Seth Earp (1851–1882)
• John Escapule (1856–1926)
• Camillus "Buck" Sydney Fly [C.S. Fly] (1849–1901)
• William H. Harris (1845–1895)
• James Butler "Wild Bill" Hickok (1837–1876)
• Benjamin J. Hodges (1880–1920?)
• John Henry "Doc" Holliday (1851–1887)
• John Baker "Texas Jack" Omohundro (1846–1880)
• Charles H. "Colorado Charlie" Utter (circa 1838–1912)
Women
• Ellen "Nellie" Cashman (1845–1925)
• Celia Ann "Mattie" Blaylock [Earp] (1850–1888)
• Josephine Sarah "Sadie" (Marcus) Earp (1861–1944)
• Urilla (Sutherland) Earp (1850–1870)
Cabinet photographs.; Cartes-de-visite (card photographs); Tintypes (prints); Gunfighters; Outlaws -- West (U.S.); West (U.S.)
- Charlie Bassett, undated (Item 1)
  Scope and Contents
  Tintype, 1 & 6/16" (W) x 1 & 10/16" (L).
- Chalkley Beeson, undated (Item 2)
  Chalkley Beeson (1855–1912).
  Tintype, 2 & 1/16" (W) x 3.25" (L).
- Chalkley Beeson, undated (Item 3)
  Tintype, 1 & 7/8" (W) x 2 & 5/16" (L).
- Billy Breakenridge, undated (Item 4)
  William Milton "Billy" Breakenridge (1846–1931).
  Tintype, 2 & 7/16" (W) x 3 & 7/16" (L).
- Curly Bill Brocius, undated (Item 5)
  William "Curly Bill" Brocius (1845–1882).
  Tintype, 2 & 5/16" (W) x 3 & 5/8" (L).
- Curly Bill Brocius, undated (Item 6)
  Tintype, 1 & 13/16" (W) x 2.75" (L).
- Nellie Cashman, 1882-1883 (Item 7)
  Ellen "Nellie" Cashman (1845–1925).
  Tintype, 2 & 9/16" (W) x 3 & 13/16" (L).
- Buffalo Bill Cody, undated (Item 8)
  William Frederick "Buffalo Bill" Cody (1846–1917).
  Tintype, 1" (W) x 1 & 9/16" (L).
- Buffalo Bill Cody, undated (Item 9)
  Tintype, 1.5" (W) x 2" (L).
- Shotgun John Collins "Butch", undated (Item 10)
  Abraham G. Graham, a.k.a. "Shotgun John Collins" (1851–1922).
  Tintype, 2-and-5/8" (W) x 4-and-1/16" (L).
- Jim Courtright, undated (Item 11)
  Timothy Isaiah Courtright, a.k.a. "Jim Courtright," "Longhair Jim," "Big Jim Courtright" (1848–1887).
  Tintype, 2.25" (W) x 3 & 5/8" (L).
- Marshall Larry Deger, undated (Item 12)
  Lawrence Edward Deger (1845–1924).
  Tintype, 2.25" (W) x 3 & 13/16" (L).
- James Earp, undated (Item 13)
  James Cooksey Earp (1841–1926).
  Tintype, 2 & 5/16" (W) x 3 & 3/8" (L).
- Josephine Marcus Earp, undated (Item 14)
  Josephine Sarah "Sadie" (Marcus) Earp (1861–1944).
  Tintype, 2 & 3/8" (W) x 3 & 5/8" (L).
- Josephine Marcus Earp, undated (Item 15)
  Tintype, 2 & 3/8" (W) x 4 & 1/16" (L).
- Mattie Blaylock Earp, undated (Item 16)
  Celia Ann "Mattie" Blaylock [Earp] (1850–1888).
  Carte-de-visite, 2 & 3/8" (W) x 3 & 5/8" (L).
  Verso advertisement for "The Kilmarnock Photographic Gallery / A. McGregor / 46 King Street [no city] / Negatives Kept. Copies Can Always Be Had."
- Morgan Earp, undated (Item 17)
  Morgan Seth Earp (1851–1882).
  Tintype, 2.5" (W) x 3.5" (L).
- Urilla Sutherland Earp, undated (Item 18)
  Urilla (Sutherland) Earp (1850–1870).
  Tintype, 1 & 11/16" (W) x 1.5" (L).
- Virgil Earp, undated (Item 19)
  Virgil Walter Earp (1843–1905).
  Carte-de-visite, 2 & 3/8" (W) x 3 & 13/16" (L).
  Verso advertisement for "Hagedorn & Suden, Jefferson City & Butler, Mo. / First-Class work Guaranteed. / Negatives retained for future orders for half price. Photographs and Ambrotypes enlarged in Oil, Crayon, Ink, Pastelle and Water Colors, to Life Size."
- Wyatt Earp, undated (Item 20)
  Wyatt Berry Stapp Earp (1848–1929).
  Tintype, 1 & 15/16" (W) x 3.25" (L).
- Wyatt Earp, undated (Item 21)
  Tintype, 2 & 1/16" (W) x 3" (L).
- Wyatt Earp, 1890-1900 (Item 22)
  Cabinet photograph, 3 & 7/8" (W) x 5 & 9/16" (L).
- John Escapule, undated (Item 23)
  John Escapule (1856–1926).
  Tintype, 1 & 7/16" (W) x 2" (L).
- John Escapule, undated (Item 24)
  Tintype, 2 & 3/8" (W) x 3 & 13/16" (L).
- C.S. Fly, undated (Item 25)
  Camillus "Buck" Sydney Fly (1849–1901).
  Carte-de-visite, 2 & 3/8" (W) x 4 & 1/16" (L).
  Verso advertisement for "Melander, Photographer / 208 Ohio St., Cor. Clark, CHICAGO."
- Bob Ford, undated (Item 26)
  Robert Newton Ford (1862–1892).
  Tintype, 6 & 3/8" (W) x 8 & 3/8" (L).
- Bob Ford, undated (Item 27)
- John Wesley Hardin, undated (Item 28)
  John Wesley Hardin (1853–1895).
  Tintype, 1 & 1/16" (W) x 1 & 11/16" (L).
- John Wesley Hardin, undated (Item 29)
  Tintype, 2 & 1/8" (W) x 3" (L).
- John Wesley Hardin, undated (Item 30)
  Tintype, 2 & 1/8" (W) x 3 & 3/8" (L).
- W. H. Harris, undated (Item 31)
  William H. Harris (1845–1895).
- Bill Hickok, undated (Item 32)
  James Butler "Wild Bill" Hickok (1837–1876).
  Tintype, 2 & 7/16" (W) x 3 & 13/16" (L).
- Bill Hickok, undated (Item 33)
  Tintype, 2 & 5/8" (W) x 3 & 13/16" (L).
- Sheriff Benjamin J. Hodges, undated (Item 34)
  Benjamin J. Hodges (1880–1920?).
  Tintype, 2 & 6/16" (W) x 3 & 7/16" (L).
- Doc J.H. Holliday, 1880-1881? (Item 35)
  John Henry "Doc" Holliday (1851–1887).
  Verso advertisement for "Le Roy & Terrill, Artists, Youngstown, O."
- Doc Holliday and Wyatt Earp, undated (Item 36)
  John Henry "Doc" Holliday (1851–1887) and Wyatt Berry Stapp Earp (1848–1929).
  Tintype, 2.25" (W) x 3 & 3/8" (L).
- Doc Henry Holliday, undated (Item 37)
  Tintype, 2.5" (W) x 3.75" (L).
- Doc John Henry Holliday, undated (Item 38)
  Tintype, 2 & 1/16" (W) x 3 & 1/16" (L).
- Doc Holliday and Wyatt Earp, undated (Item 39)
  Tintype, 2 & 7/16" (W) x 3 & 3/8" (L).
- Frank James with member of family, undated (Item 40)
  Alexander Franklin "Frank" James (1843–1915).
  Tintype, 2.25" (W) x 3.25" (L).
- Jesse James, undated (Item 41)
  Jesse Woodson James (1847–1882).
  Tintype, 1 & 1/8" (W) x 1.25" (L).
- Turkey Creek Jack Johnson, circa 1875-1880 (Item 42)
  "Turkey Creek" Jack Johnson (John Blunt?) (1852–1887).
  Tintype, 2.5" (W) x 3 & 7/8" (L).
- Turkey Creek Jack Johnson, undated (Item 43)
  Tintype, 2.5" (W) x 3 & 13/16" (L).
- Turkey Creek Jack Johnson, undated (Item 44)
- Turkey Creek Jack Johnson, undated (Item 45)
  Tintype, 1.75" (W) x 2.25" (L).
- Bill Longley, undated (Item 46)
  William Preston "Wild Bill" Longley (1851–1878).
- Marshall Christian Madsen, undated (Item 47)
  Christen Madsen Rørmose (1851–1944).
  Cabinet photograph, 4 & 1/6" (W) x 5.75" (L).
  Verso advertisement for "Parcell / North Side Square / Kirksville, Mo."
- Marshall Christian Madsen, undated (Item 48)
- Bat Masterson, 1872-1874 (Item 49)
  Bartholemew William Barclay "Bat" Masterson (1853–1921).
  Tintype, 2 & 9/16" (W) x 3 & 7/16" (L).
- Bat Masterson, undated (Item 50)
  Tintype, 4 & 7/8" (W) x 6 & 7/8" (L).
- Bat Masterson and Emma Walker Masterson, 1900-1910 (Item 51)
  Tintype, 3 & 7/16" (W) x 2.5" (L).
- Edward Masterson, undated (Item 52)
  Edward John "Ed" Masterson (1852–1878).
- Frank McLain, undated (Item 53)
  Michael Francis "Frank" McClain (1854–1902).
- Marshall Mike Meagher, undated (Item 54)
  Mike Meagher (1843–1881).
- Marshall Mike Meagher, undated (Item 55)
  Tintype, 2 & 7/16" (W) x 3 & 5/8" (L).
- Marshall Mike Meagher, undated (Item 56)
  Tintype, 2 & 3/8" (W) x 3 & 3/8" (L).
- Texas Jack Omohundro, undated (Item 57)
  John Baker "Texas Jack" Omohundro (1846–1880).
  Tintype, 2 & 11/16" (W) x 4.25" (L).
- Marshall Bob Paul, undated (Item 58)
  Robert H. "Bob" Paul (1831–1901).
  Tintype, 2 & 7/16" (W) x 3.5" (L).
- Allen [sic] Pinkerton, undated (Item 59)
  Allan Pinkerton (1819–1884).
  Tintype, 1.5" (W) x 2 & 1/16" (L).
- Sheriff John Selman, undated (Item 60)
  John Henry Selman (1839–1896).
  Tintype, 2 & 6/16" (W) x 3.25" (L).
- Sheriff John Selman, undated (Item 61)
  Tintype, 2.5" (W) x 3 & 7/16" (L).
- Constable/Sheriff John Selman, undated (Item 62)
- Luke Short, undated (Item 63)
  Luke L. Short (1854–1893).
  Tintype, 2 & 7/16" (W) x 3 & 5/16" (L).
- Marshall Tom Bear River Smith, undated (Item 64)
  Thomas James "Bear River" Smith (1830–1870).
  Tintype, 1 & 15/16" (W) x 2 & 7/16" (L).
- Frank Stilwell, undated (Item 65)
  Frank C. Stilwell (1856–1882).
  Tintype, 2 & 1/8" (W) x 2 & 15/16" (L).
- Marshall Dallas Stoudenmire, undated (Item 66)
  Dallas Stoudenmire (1845–1882).
  Tintype, 2 & 5/16" (W) x 3 & 9/16" (L).
- Marshall Dallas Stoudenmire, undated (Item 67)
  Tintype, 2 & 9/16" (W) x 3 & 5/16" (L).
- Marshall Dallas Stoudenmire and family, undated (Item 68)
  Tintype, 1 & 11/16" (W) x 2" (L).
- Marshall Heck Thomas, undated (Item 69)
  Henry Andrew "Heck" Thomas (1850–1912).
  Tintype, 3 & 3/8" (W) x 5" (L).
- Marshall Ben Thompson, undated (Item 70)
  Ben Thompson (1843–1884).
  Cabinet photograph, 4 & 5/8" (W) x 6 & 7/16" (L).
- Marshall William (Bill) Tilghman, undated (Item 71 (oversize))
  William Matthew "Bill" Tilghman Jr. (1854–1924).
  Tintype, 10 & 1/8" (W) x 14 & 1/16" (L).
- Charlie Utter, undated (Item 72)
  Charles H. "Colorado Charlie" Utter (circa 1838–1912).
  Tintype, 1 & 11/16" (W) x 2 & 7/16" (L).
- Texas Jack Vermillion, undated (Item 73)
  John Wilson "Texas Jack" or "Shoot-Your-Eye-Out" Vermillion (1842–1911).
  Tintype, 2 & 6/16" (W) x 3 & 5/8" (L).
- Inventory | David G. Chapman's and Karen D. Chapman's Tintype Collection: "Famous Men of the Old West", 2018 July 30 (Folder 1)
  Numerical list of the photographs in the collection (the numbers correspond to those on the image sleeves), with dimensions of each item in inches. 2 pages.
- Report | Karen D. Chapman, Report on the Tintypes of "Famous People of the Old West", 2018 August 4 (Folder 2)
  Includes reproductions of the photographs in the collection compared with similar images found online and elsewhere, with brief biographical sketches of the subjects. 25 pages.
- Valentine's Day card, undated (Folder 3)
  Unrelated, Victorian-era lace paper Valentine's Day card. Opens to reveal printed sentiment: "Not sunlight in its prime, / Nor moonlight's gentle rays / Is half so fair as Love, / Which brightens day by day."